[SPEAKER_00]: So, these are some questions that come from all around the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'll start with this first one, and it's in terms of persistence in practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And a friend asks, how important is having a fixed routine?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does it have a big impact on dhamma progress?
[SPEAKER_00]: Producing wholesome actions, mental qualities, or it doesn't really matter much?
[SPEAKER_00]: Should you have persistence, or can you just like... Well, I think, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it depends on every individual.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is a person with a... with tendencies of complete kind of disorganization, laziness, cannot adhere to basic worldly routine or discipline, then, yeah, it's very helpful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to, you know, get your mind in a certain sense of responsibility and stick into the... stick into the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you have the other type of an individual that would be pretty much holding the view that training, routine, being methodical, precise, is the training, is the development of dhamma, which it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just an external form.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to see which individual you are,
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you are the former, then, yeah, get some routine to keep you in check.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're the latter, then maybe, you know, become more, kind of, less routine-based and experience that, you know, mind sort of floating away without having anything fixed to do or to adhere to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because either way, that's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, the reflections you should be making on the level of practice of dhamma, the accomplishment in virtue, that's not a method, that's not a routine.
[SPEAKER_01]: That comes with insight, and repetition, and the training, and sustaining the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the routine helps you for that, you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sometimes the routine can take place instead of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all I have to do is the routine and I'm practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just get up at this, do this, do this, do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I finish the day.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a successful day because I've successfully completed my routine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not how the progress in dhamma is measured.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... and you might be kind of in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start with the routine, but then keep yourself in check in case you start taking routine in that kind of mechanical sense whereby, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: I just need to go through routine and then I'll be anxiety-free and worry-free because I completed my duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're taking it as a duty, it's not the dhamma, it's not the virtue anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the external projection of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can become like a... a robot, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unaware of what's actually going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the risk of it, always.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sometimes you can be too loose and sometimes you can be too tight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can't just always...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, routines are always good, because somebody might be already too tight and too externally projected on the sense of duty and observances and stuff that they do.
[SPEAKER_01]: In which case, no, they need to loosen up, actually, these routines, to get that sense of, whoa, my mind, my responsibility, my choice, my intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you have the other individual who's too loose, which is absolutely, and equally, no sense of responsibility or intentions, because it's too loose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing's taken internally, taken on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yeah, they would need some external
[SPEAKER_01]: adherence to the certain, you know, routines and principles, just to, you know, get them a bit into shape.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, in terms of persistence, you know, just you persistently, for example, keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just, you have to build it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, people can take, people can take persistence to mean, I'll just, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Adhere to your determination and persist.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's one way of persistence, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But persistence is exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it can be much more relaxed, yet still persistent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't have specific determination to adhere, to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the same time, you don't do certain actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are not going against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are persistent.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are persistently maintaining and protecting the basis of your virtue, that in return protects the basis of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes if you feel you're getting looser, maybe you need to build up some determination or something, but not as a rule of thumb.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I always must have this persisting determination and focus.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, because sometimes that can be the reason for you not seeing where the practice is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too tight.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, often, you know, the simile that the Buddha gave, the the the lute strings, like you want to play the music with them, but you will not be able to play the music if the strings are too tight or too loose.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to find the right balance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are one who is really trying, at least, you're really trying and you're persisting and you feel there is some
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, development, at least, you know, calmness and dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you fail, you make a mistake, you break a precept.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you just, you know, it feels like all your work is kind of lost, sometimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that the case, you think?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the attitude then, for that person?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can really feel like, this is it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, now the mind tries to go the other way, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've really messed up now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depends what precept you broke, to what extent, how much, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's like those serious precepts of killing or something like that, then, yeah, maybe you have messed up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's not on that level, then, yeah, you messed up, but not in a sense of that you cannot grow out of it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in, you messed up, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize the mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, you basically be even more aware next time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's good, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I know the mind can fall into that trap of, like, negativity about, oh, I messed up, it's unworthless and all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have to endure it, because that's pretty much the result of you messing up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't just try to, like, oh, you know, I should not think these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because feeling bad about messing up, when you were actually intentionally messed up and broke the precepts, will, as I said, make you more mindful next time, if you don't try to negate that bad feeling and allow it to endure as long as it lasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, you're taking on more weight of your action of messing up, through enduring that pain, which is a result of you messing up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, eh... as you pick up your precepts again, when the...
[SPEAKER_01]: When the challenges come, well, the memory of pain will be fresh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain of how it was when I chose to break the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you will not necessarily do it so easily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pain of regret.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The remorse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remorse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remorse, guilt, can be very useful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, can be irrational, in which case you have to be aware of that as well, and not unnecessarily fuel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have I done anything wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, then there is a base for guilt, and maybe I should endure it a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes you just feel guilty, but have I done it wrong?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, now it's irrational, and now I shall not feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, you probably have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's that...
[SPEAKER_00]: For example, okay, that inner voice, there was that one question, what should you do about that inner critic?
[SPEAKER_00]: Inner critic, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inner voice, I think that... That actually goes exactly there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as I said... You messed up, you messed up real bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: You messed up real bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're such an idiot.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll never make it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as painful as that is, you need to recognize that pretty much all of those mental states, inner critic, sense of guilt, whatever else, your mind is revolving around,
[SPEAKER_01]: are the symptoms of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're the results.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to just see them as a problem and then, oh, how do I stop the inner critic?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you actually see inner critic as an indicator of a problem that you're not seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the the power that that inner critic, that your own mind has, is the power you've been sort of feeding it through certain other actions that you are not aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, when like people have this irrational guilt constantly, or irrational critic, or something, it's the symptom of basically, when those things are not present, of your actions, of your actions and choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, you endured in a critic, don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't argue with it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, when inner critic goes away, then you keep an eye on your choices, and things you do, and things you think, and things you allow your mind to revolve around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how you're providing fuel for the inner critic later on.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, when inner critic is not there, the lack of awareness in regard to wholesomeness of your choices, actions, thoughts, themes that you entertain,
[SPEAKER_01]: The lack of awareness there, it's pretty much a way of undermining yourself, in the sense of, when the inner critic comes, you are completely at its mercy.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no... you can't say, no, stop it, to your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have to endure it, because you put yourself in that position.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can start to see the connection between your behavior, your choices, the mental themes throughout the day, things you do, things you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start seeing inner critic or that irrational guilt or whatever else your mind revolves around in these negative states, see that as a symptom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't just try to get rid of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But say, no, no, no, this is the result of something else I do when this is not present.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you start looking in that broader sense, the connection between the two will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the main thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: People don't see the connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't see the connection between day-to-day behavior and their own liability to suffer on account of their own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because for that, virtue, training, reflection, all that's required, repetitively.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And wisdom would be the result of it, when you start seeing the connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you know for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to take it on faith that a good behavior, restrained speech, restrained mind, will result in the well-being of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of makes sense, but until you see the connection directly, you will be taking it on faith, which is fine, as long as it makes you make the right effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, will come, if you are making that effort, that you're gonna see it for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: By basically keeping an eye on my behavior, virtues, wholesome as well, like, you know, you might not be breaking the precepts, but you're engaging in pointless chit-chat, gossip, idle talk, you know, a bit of slander, a bit of a bad mouth in this, a bit of that, you know, occasionally seeking distractions, unnecessarily... Basically, you are still not restrained, as you should be, and you're maintaining these unwholesome themes in your mind, that then, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're literally keeping your mind wild to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when that wild mind decides to go its own way, starts criticizing, barking at you like a mad dog, well, you kept it mad.
[SPEAKER_01]: You kept it untrained.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now you have to endure its barking and trying to bite you every now and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when it calms down, you better start training it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have developed that inner voice.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is... you were inadvertently feeding it and keeping it wild to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, this needs to be dealt with, the inner voice, the inner critic, the inner guilt-tripper, but it's actually the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not in that behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: of an underlying problem that I've been inadvertently not solving, such as you were keeping it wild through allowing it to uncontrollably go and do things and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also something that, I mean, myself, I found that when, say, going into a very extreme solitude,
[SPEAKER_00]: You get to see that inner voice very quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you've got no distractions, you get to see that inner voice very, very quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it takes a while... to calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what's the difference there?
[SPEAKER_01]: The difference is the environment of distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was none, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, without a distraction, it becomes apparent now, because then... See, if a wild dog, or a semi-wild dog,
[SPEAKER_01]: If it has its distractions, it won't bark at you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not try to bite you and harass you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take away the distractions, it's gonna start complaining.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what the mind does when you take it into solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I also remember, also in my own experience, that going into solitude and then that inner voice becoming very apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was also very irritating.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: You were averse to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was... Wow!
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't like this person and yet I'm with this person 24-7.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're ignoring even your own aversion towards it because you were... you were being distracted through allowing distraction for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, keeping yourself equally oblivious.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the important bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you get to see these things in solitude, and sooner or later you have to come out of solitude, and then realize, but I don't need to go back all the way to the distractions.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can come out of the extreme solitude, or not necessarily live perpetually in the extreme solitude, but that's still not an excuse for me to now allow this animal to go back to its distractions and become wild again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the guarding of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the animal is tamed, and you protect it from the unwholesome, you know, the baits we spoke about, which is always your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's never... that never can...
[SPEAKER_01]: The choices to accept the distraction, to accept lust, aversion, can never come from the environment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those choices are always yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Environment can provide you with hooks and baits, but you are the one always, every single time, responsible for choosing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you become aware of that inner voice, the more you practice solitude, and then you go out, you start to see that responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you realize, yeah, I can actually... this is a good balance between solitude, like non-extreme solitude, and some degrees of solitude, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, okay, so I just... all I need to do is just protect this animal, this animal, not feed it distractions, lust, and aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then there is no basis for it to be barking at you and attacking you, because it's still calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not being agitated by things you allow it to agitate.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's also...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, when I saw that the inner voice that I wasn't liking was a complaining voice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when everything... when there was no distraction...
[SPEAKER_00]: That was clear that my mind was just complaining all the time about everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was nothing to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was nothing to care.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I never noticed how much I was doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it was just all the time complaining.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, all of that, all of that energy behind all that complaining has been generated, cultivated.
[SPEAKER_01]: The wildness of that animal has been maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the choices of distraction, aversion, lust, you know, not even major sort of, you know, lust or desires or something, but still, on a day-to-day basis, you kept your mind, that animal, you were allowing it to be sort of distracted, dependent on the external sense objects, one way or the other, and when that's taken away, it was left with that aversion now, of complaining, attacking, barking, being a nuisance.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you didn't allow that animal to become distracted, there would be no basis for its complaining, because it can't calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's in a critic, complaining voice, guilt-tripping voice, you realize that that's a symptom of the choices, themes that I cultivate, maintain, and I'm careless about throughout the day, when I'm not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, when the mind is not complaining and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just basically become more aware of things you choose to, you know, do by body, by speech, by mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And really, as I said, it's not this external observance of be virtuous, be virtuous.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a direct connection between every single time you make this choice and how much, whether you, whether you fuel, whether you encourage animal, animal's wildness or whether you're taming it through your choices.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you adhere to them rightly, it won't take long before you realize, oh, it's actually tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Solitude is a good indicator.
[SPEAKER_01]: Solitude reveals the symptoms, if there are any.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: If a monk doesn't develop... doesn't delight in solitude, doesn't, you know, make himself want solitude, he'll never understand the nature of his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, why wouldn't he want solitude?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would a wild animal not want to become aware of its wildness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's unpleasant, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's dependent on distractions and solitude takes those away, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of that failure, again, some... another friend asked...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know if we can say anything more on the subject, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of failure, when you feel like you've let others down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say you fail your degree and feel miserable that you let your family down and see very little hope for the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he's quite concerned about or seems to be overwhelmed by letting others down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why is that a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels unpleasant here and now, when others are disappointed with you, and that's why it's a problem for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, say you have a person you don't care about, you don't even know, and they just stop you on the street and say, I'm really disappointed in you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't really care.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might want to curiously find out why, but who is this person to be disappointed with me anyway?
[SPEAKER_01]: So you want to recognize that the problem is, you don't really want the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't want a pain of it, you should have been careful with your ambitions beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because each time you want to achieve something, attain something, get something, there is a liability... you have to take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you might not succeed to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm not saying you shouldn't be ambitious.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just saying don't take it for granted, but take responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you keep the possibility of failure in your mind, well, the disappointment of others will already be implicit in that, and it will not surprise you or overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, given that now you're overwhelmed, pretty much you have to endure the pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can't... it won't last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the pain fades away,
[SPEAKER_01]: Reconsider your ambition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Find something else if you want to be ambitious about and do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't just sort of blindly commit to it and forget that, yeah, you might not succeed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, and, you know, also, fundamentally, others can always find reasons to be disappointed with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's another thing perhaps you should re-evaluate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasing others.
[SPEAKER_01]: How far you want to go with that, because, you know, if you start going that way, it is endless.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can never please others, because they would always have opinions and views and everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, you don't ignore, you know, others in that sense, but especially, you know, family, people you live with, but at the same time, the point will come where you do need to draw some sort of line for yourself and for others, as like, well, yeah, but this is my life and my choices, my responsibility, my results.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, accept, you know, the nagging, or being upset, or whatever, as part of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to have ill will on account of that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you are not clear with yourself, well, you will not be clear in regard to where that line is, and then...
[SPEAKER_00]: When people praise you, or blame you, you just... Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not be able to sort of withstand it without losing perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, now it feels like, oh, it's all in there or something, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure that person has experienced this, others being disappointed with them before, in regard to something, something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it came, and it went.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't need to completely dismiss it, but you certainly shouldn't be like, oh, I must be pleasing others, because even that, it's rooted just because you don't want to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, when you feel like, I must please others, it's because it's too unpleasant for me, when others are displeased for me, eh, with me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, that's impossible to achieve.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think you can avoid the pain by preventing or providing others with what they want,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just gonna suffer more.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the, in that one sutta, the Buddha says it, nobody is fully blamed, fully praised.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody is praised all the time, or blamed all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even Tathāgata was blamed, and even the voice people are sometimes praised.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to accept that, and accept that really the issue with that is like, again, you don't lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I failed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I could have done better.
[SPEAKER_01]: I should try and do better.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, don't become irrational about it in a sense of, oh, but, but they're so disappointed, worried, worried.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's actually not about others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about you not wanting the unpleasantness of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you think by managing and providing others what they want, you can avoid this dukkha that you have to endure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to avoid the dukkha that you can endure, is... that you are enduring, is by enduring it and taking responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not trying to manage the external world in account to get rid of that which you're averse to.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's really the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem of others being disappointed, the problem of others blaming you or something, is that just feels painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't want to deal with that pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes they have a point, sometimes they don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you want to maintain that perspective, you have to accept what you're feeling on account of others, not try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, by accepting the pain, you will also not have ill will towards them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not trying to get rid of dukkha, except the responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're enduring it, you're seeing it for what it is, so there's no aversion towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you get to see what they're complaining, what they're upset, what they're disappointed about, and it's like, actually, yeah, they have a point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And from that perspective, you will get to actually act accordingly and upgrade your behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also, sometimes you'll see, no, they're completely irrational.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just want... they just want what they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't really even care about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just want what they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in that case, you will not entertain that and feed that further.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll not be angry about it either, but you will certainly be able to remain unmovable.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to cultivate a sense of urgency as a lay person?
[SPEAKER_00]: What would be a practical approach to find motivation to make dhamma practice a priority as a lay person?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, incessant reflection on the nature of your situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to make the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't think about it, the mind forgets, drifts away, gets pulled with sensuality, you lose sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have to think about things that you are subjected to in that world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes it might be like a little prompt, sometimes you might just have to sit and dwell on everything that could go wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that will bring you with anxiety and sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you already have it, you don't need to dwell on these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want that kind of a bit of a sharpness to it, because otherwise you can't move towards the direction of dhamma at all, sensuality is too overwhelming, then yeah,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure things would have happened to everyone in their life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that they don't want to think about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, think about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it can happen again.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think about the fact that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Liability to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your priority is sensuality and not dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're struggling to get out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're completely trapped.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, like when sensuality comes, they would not necessarily feel the sense of urgency to restrain themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to dwell on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to sustain that context that will keep things urgent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, always whoever asks that question, they recognize that when they lose the urgency, they kind of go back to sensuality and lose the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, that is not uncommon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even in the suttas, the Buddha would basically scare monks, light the fire under them, by reminding them what's still there, so they get the sense of urgency, because they still have work to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they just got negligent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to find something and then, yeah, cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it runs out, find another thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will bring a bit of anxiety and sense of urgency, so that you can actually sustain your precepts and practice towards dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't wait till it's too late.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't wait until the world actually throws something at you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fill you with anxiety and fear and be too much to handle.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, start preparing yourself and training yourself for it already.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can, as I said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just choose the right themes and it will arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sickness, aging, death, you know, any basically form of dukkha, discomfort, suffering you experienced, anything you fear you might, you would experience, anything you don't experience and you don't think about it, all of that is all revealing that you're still liable to these things, you're still liable to be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think about it and you will feel, oh, I need to address this urgently.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be a natural outcome.